Congress makes 50 new crimes per year
can you imagine such a thing 50 new
crimes per year so this is something
that was legal last year is a felony
this year and will send you to jail or
prison that's just not normal normal
countries don't do things like that
[Music]
I heard you speak a little bit about the
living conditions and how prison reform
is a huge concern of yours now now I've
known other high-profile cases the
minute they start to speak on anything
immediately they're shipped around you
found a way through your communication
which I read through the Huffington Post
found a way to not be affected by the
diesel therapy and for those people that
don't know what usual therapy is I'm
what you explained it but explain how
your how you're able to continue outing
the prison system and the work that
needed to be done and not getting
shipped around it was an odyssey before
I went to prison one of my attorneys
said hey once you get comfortable write
us a letter and we'll e-mail it around
to your supporters there were like 600
people who had signed on to an email
list just wanting an update to see how I
was so six weeks in I wrote this letter
and I told a couple of stories that I
didn't even realize were we're stories
about the guards breaking the law in
targeting me so I sent it to my
attorneys I didn't realize that one of
my attorneys was friends with Arianna
Huffington and so she sent it to Arianna
and Arianna plastered it as this banner
headline on the Huffington Post I got
more than a million hits and within days
it had been picked up by every major
newspaper all the network news broadcast
CNN came to the Jake Tapper came to the
prison to interview me I was on NPR from
the prison I mean it was ridiculous and
so and so the guards started threatening
me and then there was one who was
actually friendly like only when we were
alone he was friendly he was supportive
he actually told me once that he thought
it was a miscarriage of justice that I
was in there
and he said to me hey you need to you
need to watch out they're talking about
putting you in diesel therapy
I said what's that I had never heard of
it before
well what it is is if you're a prisoner
who's deemed to be something of a
troublemaker they will put you in
transit status now they'll put you on a
prison bus send you to USP Kane in the
penitentiary which is a transportation
hub for the Northeast you might be in
Canaan for a week a month six months
whatever you don't know they put you on
another bus to Harrisburg in Harrisburg
they put you on a con air flight to USP
Atlanta you stay there for a period of
time then they send you to Oklahoma City
which is the national transportation hub
from there maybe you go to Yankton or
Springfield or Denver or Lompoc or
whatever well they can keep you in
transit status for two years the thing
is is when you're in transit status you
don't have access to email to a phone or
to a pen and paper it's it's a way to
legally silence you so what I did is I
wrote about this immediately and I sent
it to Arianna and she immediately
published it at the huffington post and
again it just it went viral it went
everywhere well Oliver Stone and John
Cusack tweeted it they tweeted hands off
John Kiriakou and the peace group code
pink asked all of their members to call
the office of the head of the Bureau of
Prisons and complain they logged 1,600
calls to the Bureau of Prisons saying
you better not put him in diesel therapy
and they all backed off all those Bo P
officials they all backed off and I knew
that I was Teflon after that so what I
did is I filed a Freedom of Information
Act request on myself and it was
actually very quick it only took about
four weeks but I got a big fat package
of stuff back most of it was useless it
was my visitor list it was my medical
records - stupid stuff right but there
were eight pages in there that were very
clearly marked FOIA exempt do not
release to inmate
so it was one of two situations either
the person doing the FOIA request was so
friggin stupid that they didn't see
these giant red block letters at the top
and bottom saying do not release the
inmate or somebody took pity on me and
they released it to me on purpose so
what it was was a series of memos going
back and forth between the warden and
the Bo P saying what do we do with this
guy he's famous and we're not sure what
to do and then finally the warden wrote
a it wasn't even a memo so much as it
was like a sign in these huge capital
letter block letters that went all
around the prison and it said caution
inmate has access to the media and then
underneath that it said inmate is not to
have any contact with the public has
access to the media so I knew I had him
by the balls I knew that I could say
anything that I wanted and there was
nothing they could do to me and so
that's what I did I ended up writing 19
blog posts and they became this book I
called them letters from Loreto and I
incorporated them into this before the
book was even published I won the pen
First Amendment award from the pen
center USA which is like the preeminent
journalistic freedom organization so
prison was a quite an experience for you
with with what you've accomplished and
seeing things I mean it's not very often
that somebody from one side of the law
from the side you Iran gets to see it
from a complete opposite point of view
aside from being away from your children
what was for you probably the toughest
portion of the whole prison sentence you
know it was it was brown hot day it's
every day is exactly like every other
day and it doesn't matter if it's you
know July 4th or it's Christmas or it's
a Sunday or whatever every day is
exactly like the next and or the one
before that was one thing that that got
old really really fast the other thing
that bothered me was these arbitrary
nonsensical rules most these guys
it's there they were they were scrubs
from the military they washed out of the
local police academy they couldn't get a
job doing anything else and literally
the only qualifications you need to be a
prison guard or you have to be either
working on a GED or with the GED and or
a high school diploma and never
convicted of a felony that's it so the
cream of the crop they're not um and
then having to you know answer to these
guys that that took some getting used to
and a lot of them would try to bait me
and I never took the bait
never which just wouldn't raise them
more there was one cop he had a
reputation of being the worst of the
worst he was the only he was the only
guard who wore a stab vest because he
was he was just such a total psychopath
that he was justifiably worried that
somebody was going to stab him he even
covered up his name with a piece of
electrical tape because he didn't want
anybody to you know get released and
then come looking for him so one of the
Italians Mike my closest friend in
prison said something to him one day he
said hey his name was blue his nickname
was blue we don't know what his real
name he said hey blue where are you
gonna be stationed the next quarter and
he said um I'm gonna be in central one
and he said the Italian said uh my
friend Johnson is in central one and
blue said the CIA guy and the Italian
said yeah blue says I never mess with
that guy and the Italian said yeah why
not and he said that's all I need I work
my eight-hour day and then I go to my
car and CNN's waiting for me he said no
thanks and that's how they all ended up
being they just left me alone that's
good that's good that's yeah unfortunate
not everybody gets that same experience
but it's good that you found a way to
really work the system to your benefit
what were some of the biggest reforms
you said there's a lot of reform needed
from what you've seen what just to talk
just in just a second on that what was
the real issues that you saw the the
biggest overall like
mirela issue is it has to be sentencing
reform you know these draconian drug
sentences that we have they have to be
and I'm not talking about like just
curtail they need to be dispensed with
we lock up more people than any other
country in the world I mean you've heard
the statistic it's chilling but it's
true we have 5% of the world's
population and 25% of the world's prison
population that's that's not an accident
we put ourselves in that position
Congress makes 50 new crimes per year
can you imagine such a thing 50 new
crimes per year so this is something
that was legal last year is a felony
this year and will send you to jail or
prison that's just not normal normal
countries don't do things like that
we've got to start with drug laws and
drug sentencing on them on a more
day-to-day level it's got to be medical
care I mean in the very short time that
I was in prison I saw four guys die for
no reason
all from preventable illnesses and the
shame of it is that nobody gave a
that they died
you know nobody intervened try to help
them and and that's that's just morally
wrong you know the government is is
duty-bound legally bound to provide
adequate medical care and they don't now
if you want to get a little bit farther
down in the weeds food you know my first
full day in prison one of the Italians
said oh it's Friday it's fish day I said
yeah well I like fish because not this
fish we call it Seward trout he said
don't ever eat the fish the cafeteria
and there are these boxes stacked up
behind the the chow line and they're
marked Alaskan Pollock product of China
which I didn't understand I still don't
understand and then underneath that it
said feed use only not for human
consumption and that was the that was
the fish that we eat every single week
for the next two years
it was Friday huh it was yeah fish
Friday was animal feed
now there was one terrible incident that
actually made the press where the the
slaughterhouse the packaging and
slaughterhouse that provided prisons in
our area with with ground beef it was
based in Texas and they accidentally
mislabeled a shipment of ground beef it
was actually a shipment of dog food and
it was mislabeled as ground beef and
they sent it to us and we ate it well
the shame was not even that we ate dog
food the shame was that nobody even
realized we had eaten dog food because
it tasted exactly the same as the ground
beef that we always ate that's how low
the quality of the food is it's not
human quality food this company was
fined eighteen thousand dollars payable
to the US Treasury so we never could we
never got any of it even indirectly but
that just it's just one example of how
prisoners are treated as subhumans so
having money in prison
Audrey Missouri oh yeah and and what I
ended up doing is is you know I ended up
I ended up eating all my meals with the
Italians and so you know four or five
days a week they cooked they had a
crooked cop on payroll he would bring in
pork loin and chicken breast and white
wine for the marsala sauce and fresh
tomatoes and and mushrooms and I
actually gained 25 pounds in prison
because the way the Italians cooked I
mean I eat like a king otherwise you're
exactly right what you do is you go to
commissary and you buy bags of chicken
and tuna and you know instant rice and
spices and and you just cook for
yourself it's the only thing you can do
you know it's pretty sad that uh you
know you guys have a booze idea jumping
from rooftops you guys shooting down
with an ak-47 splats on the ground and
you find a way to to keep them alive and
bring them back to health
meanwhile you got guys sitting you got
Americans sitting in a federal prison
aren't dying from gunshots there they're
slowly dying but yet there's there's
nobody to there to help them it's almost
like you're better off being from
somewhere else or being somewhere else
altogether yeah this is what you're
saying is not a joke you're actually not
at all
money what you're saying is that
al-qaeda prisoners get better food and
better medical care than American
prisoners and that's the honest to God's
truth well hopefully people like you
that continue to to fight this seemingly
uphill fight maybe at some point
something that you're doing or something
that many others are doing and I like to
include myself in that fight maybe
something what happened at some point so
after getting out of prison you worked
at home as a consultant for a medical
firm what was that like is you you were
working from home now how much halfway
house time did they give you no not a
single day that was my punishment for
going public all the time so I deserved
I did the whole stretch no good time
nothing I had my good time and I there's
of course a federal mandatory 90 days or
10% of whom could find that whichever is
less I ended up with 87 days of home
confinement so a good friend of mine is
his dad and mom were both doctors and
they put me on the payroll just to you
know help them get their business up and
running that lasted only for the period
that I was on home confinement and then
it went briefly to up to a think-tank
here in Washington the oldest think-tank
in town focusing on prison reform issues
and then I ended up getting my own daily
two-hour radio show I've got a
syndicated newspaper column every week
that runs in 220 small town papers
around the country and and I speak at
colleges and universities not only
around the United States but all over
Western Europe I go to Europe all the
time talking about the the American
prison system and what's wrong with it
all of these issues that you now are
able to identify how much of this were
you aware of prior to going through it
yourself
none of it so with that said in your
next think-tank are you guys trying to
find a focus on how you bring this
awareness to the population masses of
people that do not know that it exists
that are just naive to the whole concept
how do you do that oh yeah I do that
mostly well on my radio show we do a
30-minute segment every Thursday called
called criminal injustice in which we we
interview a reporter who covers criminal
justice issues and the editor-in-chief
of prison legal news magazine all right
we have them every Thursday for a half
an hour and we talk about exactly these
issues we've got a good listener ship
we've got about 35,000 people that
download the podcast every day and then
this is almost exclusively what I write
about in my in my columns because nobody
pays any attention to these issues you
know we have so much to learn from our
European allies about about recidivism
and and job training and education and
we think we're smarter than everybody
else and we're not we have a lot to
learn and so I work hard to get the word
out I've been fortunate on Capitol Hill
too because I've talked to a whole bunch
of congressmen and a handful of senators
and this is something where we're the
right and the left have come together so
you've got the Progressive Caucus and
the freedom caucus the the Tea Party
that are agreeing on these issues for
different reasons but they still agree
that especially on drug sentencing laws
that these laws have to go I'm glad to
see somebody out there is putting in
time into this because I and where can
people find your radio show your podcast
information that you're putting out
there should help bring awareness where
do people go for this sure it's if
you're in the Washington area it's on
from 4 to 6 p.m. on 105.5 FM or a 13 90
a.m. that's Washington DC otherwise
we're it's called loud and clear and
we're podcast on itunes i heart radio
and Spreaker and an MSNBC interview you
stated people are trained to live for a
living they lie to everybody you have to
be able to separate
lying from work for the betterment of
the country and lying just for the sake
of lying today looking back what is true
for you when it comes to that statement
that you made if you have a statement
and that statement is exactly why you
can't believe the likes of Gina Haskell
because at the CIA we are trained liars
your job is to recruit spies to steal
secrets and in order to recruit spies
you have to convince those people that
you are their best friend in the world
that takes a lot of acting a lot of
lying the problem is as I told Chris
Hayes in that interview a lot of guys
don't know when to turn it off they lie
to their wives they lie to their bosses
and this is why the CIA has the highest
divorce rate in all of the US government
it's over 75 percent because they just
don't know when to turn it off well
you've got to know when to turn it off
sometimes lying is good for the country
because you're recruiting somebody who's
going to help to to protect the country
sometimes lying is bad for everybody and
you know then it's it's never acceptable
you just have to have a moral compass an
ethical compass and and know in your
heart that you're doing the right thing
guys I'm r dot ban federal prison time
consulting every day people helping
people community is met with one day at
a time thank you very much John how
about I mean any day any time take care
[Music]